Subtitles by
Tushtu
Hey, kutta
Hey, Kunjunni
Hey!
You'll fall on face
Instead of nodding off like this, why don't you clear the bed and sleep on it?
Hasn't the Sir come yet?
If he had come, wouldn't you see him?
It's past 12 ...
This is really not done.
Just wait for him to get here.
This has been going on for a while
I will end this practice from today onwards
What, the concert?
No, the side business after the concert!
The more I let it go, the worse it becomes.
There's no point in putting it so lightly
You need to be direct
I'll tell him!
What, you don't think he'd listen to me?
Regardless of his greatness as a singer
If my expression changes, he'll quake. That goes for both brothers.
But if only your expression would change. Right?
You weren't asleep?
Uncle, why can't you have a serious talk with him?
Well, in that case, can't you do the same?
There are limits to what I can discuss with him.
You can rebuke him
Can I do that?
I've thought about it several times. However,
When I see that walk, laugh and demeanor, I cannot help but think of your father
I have not had the audacity to sit before him except during a concert
Everywhere he went, he had devotees
How many temptations
And that too, at such important people's places.
And he has never failed.
Music was God to him
When the son of a man like that...
God save us.
Those are merely other people's beliefs.
Music is from the heart
It doesn't disappear just because you had a few drinks.
And if that's the case, these Western folk partake quite often and there's music.
Therefore, there shouldn't be any music there!
Thus, that's not the truth.
Each group has its own practices and beliefs.
And that's the right way.
I've seen several great artists get sloshed
before a performance.
You must remember one thing
We are supposed to consume alcohol; it must not consume us
It doesn't matter which artists comes to me
I will show him a great time before he leaves.
Artists are the wealth of the country.
We must respect them
Love them
Now, look, the committee is not going to reimburse me for all this.
It'll go straight from my pocket!
Let it go!
It's for art!
The satisfaction my soul gets is enough.
I'm done.
I think I overdid it a bit.
If three people share one bottle, it's bad luck to not finish it!
Let's finish this off.
Ah no, they're all waiting for me.
Let them wait!
You only need to go once we have done this properly.
Ah sorry, that won't work out.
It's my younger brother and uncle.
Uncle?
Don't you know Pallavoor Parameshwaran Nair?
He's the king of the mrithangam (drum).
His own uncle.
He's not only my uncle
He is my guru as well. He even taught the mrithangam to my father.
Oho, so your father was in the same line of work as well.
What country are you from!?
Haven't you heard of Payyannoor Devanarayana Namboodri?
Who is he?
Well ...
To be honest, I haven't heard of him.
When I'm busy with my business I occasionally dabble in the arts.
Hey. A talent like that has never been seen here.
Really?
Then, next year, his concert is enough for us. What do you think?
Then your dead father needs to figure it out!
He passed away around 15 years ago.
What a loss. An eternal loss.
If I stay here any longer, we cannot part on good terms.
Huh? What ...
That's how it is.
You got tired of waiting, right?
Gopi...
As they say, it just happened.
The committee folk asked me to come over to give me the rest of the money.
We were chatting for a while and I didn't realize how time had flown
Call everyone. Let's head out.
Why are you looking at me like that?
They entertained you really well, didn't they?
Entertainment?
They poured a bit of something with my juice.
Just a bit.
I have to travel for a few hours, right?
It relieves the fatigue.
But, this is not good for us at all.
Do you know how much sister-in-law worries?
Nobody in our family has this habit.
Save the sermon for later.
Call the others; let's go.
There's no need to travel today.
They've all gone to bed.
Everyone knows you've started this habit.
But nobody needs to know that it has reached this state
Especially Uncle.
He doesn't merely treat you with the respect befitting just his relative, or daughter's husband.
Please, don't worry him.
I don't drink excessively as you guys think.
I'm starting to understand that.
In any case, we will only leave in the morning.
Aunty, you know the guy who just moved in next door?
A baldy?
He wants to know all kinds of things.
Do you sing?
Do you dance?
And then, what do people here know?
I went to him with some milk and he had me there for an hour with his questions.
Oh wow, that looks beautiful
You should give it to me once it's done
Appu!
Don't you have anything to read or study?
It took you an hour to deliver some milk
Check out the loitering police
Oh Radha. Have you already started with your stitching in the morning?
Go to the kitchen.
Can't you see your sister-in-law toiling away alone?
Father, your hot water for the bath is ready.
Devu, haven't the kids returned?
No, they haven't.
They said they'd be back in the night.
Ramani has been up all night waiting for them.
Where is that girl?
I had sent her over here.
She must be next door or something.
She's so lazy. All she wants to do is dress up and loll about.
I told her it was OK.
If she comes in contact with the heat, or if she burns herself at the fire, that's enough for her brothers.
I won't hear the end of their complaints about making her work and exhaust herself.
Women should be knowledgeable about these things.
When she joins a new household soon, will her brothers be around to help with the kitchen work?
I think they've arrived. Can you keep an eye on this?
Here you go.
Can you put this away?
Yes, sir
Did you get worried when we didn't turn up last night?
Oh no. It's not like you're all little kids.
Sure, sure. You probably haven't slept all night.
Don't I know her?
Father, why don't you come in for some tea?
I'll have tea at home.
Who knows what's happening there now!
Let's go!
It's hard to tell when these festival concerts start or end. Can't be sure of anything!
Were you worried?
Oh, not at all. Mother and grandfather worried.
There's no need to talk to Mother or Ramani about what happened yesterday.
If someone asks, there are reasons.
Basically, you want me to lie.
Unpleasant truths don't need to be stated.
Unpleasant actions don't need to be committed.
That, I promise.
There have been several promises like this in the past.
This is not like that!
This ... is for sure.
What are you guys whispering about outside instead of coming in?
The things which happened yesterday. The elephant went wild!
Oh no! And then?
And then... Nothing happened, but the concert started at 2pm.
What, what happened?
Father, the elephant attacked!
And then?
And then ... oh, the things which happened, Grandfather.
Gopi, why don't you tell them?
And how am I supposed to tell them?
I need to bathe and eat something!
What's there to eat, mother?
There's dosa (savory crepe).
And was the elephant contained, Gopi?
The elephant ...
Grandfather, it's time I went to the office. I'll tell you once I get back.
What, what?
I wonder which elephant it was ...
Mother ... mother ... MOTHER!
What, what happened?
I called mother.
To tell her that I'm leaving
Do you really need to rend your throat screaming like a demoness?
You really scared me. I thought something terrible had happened.
No, it's not that. I missed Gopiettan.
So what? Don't you know how to get there by yourself?
Then, get going!
I didn't get any sleep last night and I had just managed to fall asleep. Now, that's gone.
I'm here for an audit.
I'm from Piravam.
Sir, are you here with your family?
No, I'm here alone.
I have met your mother and grandfather.
In any case, I'm quite lucky to have gotten that house.
Because I can tell people at home that I was Kalloor Ramanathan's neighbor for a while
You shouldn't be this arrogant
Can't you turn around when someone's calling you?
In any case, I get the hint. Nowadays you always ignore me.
She's my cousin.
Daughter of my uncle.
Which means, she's your betrothed, right?
That's right
I'll leave you to talk.
Devi, you need to cultivate some manners.
Is it right to throw a tantrum when I'm speaking to someone?
What would he think?
He can get lost.
It looks really full. We can catch the next bus. Also, I want to talk to you about something.
You can take the next bus. You can get to your college whenever you like.
If I'm not in my seat by 10, the superintendent will mark me as absent. That's the kind of ass he is.
Gopietta!
Can you stop?
Ah, the artist has arrived!
Was there a concert yesterday?
The superintendent has asked to see you.
For what?
Must be to organize a concert!
Sir?
Yes?
I was told to meet you?
It's not because I have any desire to meet you.
What are you playing at?
There was a concert by my brother yesterday.
I don't run my office based on your brother's concerts!
An urgent file was requested by the RDO.
What excuse will I give?
You only care about concerts. Who do you think you are? Yesudas?
Sir, there's no need to get so worked up.
I'll take half a day off.
Leave? What if I don't grant the leave?
Sir, this isn't something that you need to grant.
Usually, people take the leave.
One of these days, I'll teach you a lesson.
That's it right?
You're not going to kill me by hanging right?
Let me see if I can start work without you granting me leave.
You cannot meet the RDO regarding the office without my permission!
Who's the RDO? God?
Let me see if I can meet him.
God, huh?
Let him come. I'll deal with him.
OK, OK, I'll ask him.
It's a complaint about you.
The superintendent.
Why are you the office rebel?
Sir, I was half an hour late.
He didn't allow me to put it down as leave either.
Ah, sit.
I heard that you said something disrespectful about me ... ?
Sir, do you really think so?
Na, I just asked for the heck of it since he brought it up.
Isn't he aware that we knew each other before this job?
I haven't mentioned it to anyone, sir.
I don't want people to think I'm taking advantage of our relationship
Don't you need to clock in?
I'll take half the day off
As if you should use your vacation days to satisfy your stubbornness.
Connect me to the superintendent
He's here.
Can you send the attendance register over?
Man, all government offices have this kind of jealousy
Back in the village office
I distinctly remember him kicking me around because of a few plays I did
Once they put on the IAS crown, there's no respect for theater or music.
I'm free till the afternoon
Till then, you're going to work here
We can have some music and arts for a bit, what say?
No vistors till the afternoon; I'm very busy.
OK, sir.
Please stay
Doing the deepaaradhana is comforting now
What's your name?
Is there anything wrong in me knowing it?
Ah it's Vijayan
Come
Have a seat inside
No, can't sit down. I'm going home tomorrow since it's a second Saturday.
So I don't need milk tomorrow and the day after tomorrow. Do tell your mother.
Will do.
I'll take your leave. OK.
Who's playing the veena?
That's my younger sister, Radha.
Does your sister sing as well?
No, she is mute.
Sorry, I didn't know.
No, it's not a problem.
I should go
Aha, you're sitting here quite safely
You took a lot of money off me in that game the day-before-yesterday
Call sister-in-law; we'll play a turn.
Don't cheat OK?
As if
Mother's game!
Listen, hit it fully on the line
Ammai, look go for the red!
Now she'll play by herself for half an hour. Let's kill time talking about something.
Then, can I ask something?
Is the elephant story made-up or true?
Elephant story? Which elephant?
Oh, at the concert. That's not made up!
She broke rank. It could've been a big problem.
Luckily it was a female elephant. She calmed down quickly.
Play quickly!
Don't break my concentration; let me play!
Does a female elephant go wild?
A female elephant doesn't go wild, does it?
Actually, now I'm not sure if it were male or female
Do you really want to put on this show for me?
I've known you since you were born
I wanted to tell you
That brother has started some undesirable habits
I'll tell you later
I know, Gopi
I've known for a while
In the beginning, I thought it was just medicine
Only later did I understand
That he was adding something else to the medicine
I'm tired of talking about it
Mother, it's your turn!
What happened, mother?
Nothing happened!
Red, where's the red coin?
We knocked that in a while back!
Then, what's the point of playing!?
Hey, Father is coming!
It seems that everyone is playing all the time here
Tomorrow and day after are holidays
Oh, so you don't need to open your books at all for the next two days!
Instead of wasting time playing, can't you do your vocal exercises?
I'll do it early in the morning tomorrow.
I don't need to go into work tomorrow since it's a holiday tomorrow.
I've seen so many holidays
Ever since he got this government job, I have never heard him sing apart from the concerts.
Sister-in-law, didn't I sing early in the morning for 2 hours?
Why are you needlessly making her lie?
Appu!
Go call grandmother and grandfather
Music is like a lamp
If you polish it daily, it will shine like gold.
If not
It will be covered in a patina, dark, and look dirty
And then, you cannot clean it
Brother has mentioned this before
If you choose a government job as your profession, that's fine.
But this is a gift
For generations, the art we received from Saraswati
was taught to me by Father
and taught to you by me
and it must be you who must teaches it to the next generation
I'll focus my energies on that
Sometimes when I hear his words and way of speaking, he truly is his father
Grandfather, were you sleeping?
Oh, no.
I already have one or two of these
Well, it won't be anything like this
This is for Mother
This is for mother and son
And this is for the official
Here
Where's Radha?
Brother ..
Come closer, child
Do you like it?
Huh?
Didn't you buy anything for yourself?
I got some medicine for myself.
My stomach isn't well
Ramani, please put this inside
He's truly his father's son
He can't get any sleep if he hasn't blown all his cash on something
What's the point in hoarding it?
Ah Gopi, did you drop by Uncle's on your way back?
No
Ah, Devi's quite troubled over there
Something about you not smiling at her
Or that you didn't take her along with you. Something like that
And so, she didn't go to college and headed straight home
She's not like Ramani
She gets sulky very quickly
And she gets over it as quickly
He's also got some of that as well
They're kids right? They can be allowed some laxity
That's right
OK then, I'll just sing and dance on the road
Oh please, nothing as drastic as that!
Now, why are we simply delaying that?
We were thinking it should be after Radha's
Who's going to come for her?
What do you think about advertising in the newspapers again?
Nothing will come of that, Mother
You know how it goes with newspaper ads
They're only interested in the number of lakhs they can get
They don't care if she has eyes, arms, legs, or noses
Well, that's how it is
Who would love a mute?
Being mute is an ailment for humans, Mother, not for goats or cows
That's enough
She's in the next room
The towel and soap is ready for your bath. Come.
Ammai, do you think I'm a grinch?
No, I've never thought that
I've thought he's just a killjoy
What?
What happened?
Oh, nothing!
Brother says I don't know how to kill time
Before, when he used to come here, it was such a ruckus
Back then, Ramani studied dance
When the two got together, it was all dancing and singing
And Uncle would join in with the mrithangam
It was so much fun
Raman was quite different back then
Then he'd cook up so many wacky things
I'm also getting used to some wacky things
This much fooling around is not required
Look, Ammai, she's pinching me!
Why are you bothering him?
She's simply bugging me ... hey!
Gopietta, let go!
I'm a killjoy, is it?
Oh God, what would happen if Mother saw us?
So what?
I have a right
You heard what Ammai said
About brother and sister-in-law
Then, that means Ammai has seen stuff like this before!
Why is your face so red?
What's with this girl?
Madhavi, I'm starving, can you serve some food?
Let me iron this first
Ah, Gopi ...
Did she mention an event at her college?
Yes, she mentioned it, but it wouldn't be right if I did it.
This is also not right.
What isn't right, Uncle?
We want to live here without fear
Can we live like this day and night making drum noises?
I don't understand
You don't need to understand
I'll tell Raman
He'll understand quickly
He's also proficient in these martial arts
Either way, we should not delay and do this as soon as possible
We're not in a hurry
Understood, understood
Ramani, did you tell him?
He's taking a bath. He'll be here soon.
Start, child
Ramani, can you get two ounces of that medicine?
My stomach doesn't feel good.
Quickly, Ramani
Brother, did you call for me?
Ah, did you see that Ammai and Devi are here?
I saw
Devi asked for a song and you said that wasn't possible
It's best if you do it. What do I know about music?
Then, why did I work so hard, all these years?
Is it enough that you set the scale and be a backup singer?
If I touch it, it'll become a devotional
Here, take it
Let it be a natthe
Since it's light music, some improvisation is alright.
I knew he was trouble the minute I saw him
Just because they talked, should we misunderstand what happened?
Let them talk
Getting prasadam, and putting the sandalwood paste on his forehead. What's the need for all that?
You get prasadam at the temple
Do you come to the temple to talk to women?
You come to worship
And what laughter and boyish mannerisms
If he was a young man, I'd get it but he's an old man.
Please come inside.
No need.
What's the meaning of this?
Of what?
Don't you know?
I saw you perform kathakali
Sorry.
Sorry!?
If you come to our neighborhood and do these filthy things, you won't leave this body
Are you threatening me?
No need for that
What's your intent behind enacting this romance?
To deceive her?
Or for timepass?
It was timepass in the beginning
until I found out she was a mute
Now, I'm serious
I would like to marry Radha
with everyone's blessings
It's been five years since my wife passed
I've told Radha all this
If you don't think this is a big shortcoming, I shall mail my father asking him to come here
What do you say?
We need to think about it
Alright, think about it
You must let me know even if your reply isn't positive
And if so, I will not bother you by staying here
I'm sorry, Vijayan. Sorry.
Does he know that she is a mute?
He knows
He has been here a few times
He has a nice disposition
How many lakhs did he request?
He didn't say anything about that
Maybe he has entrusted all that to his relatives
He doesn't seem like that kind of person
Then, it must be due to pity
I fear that kind the most
Do you remember, we had someone like that once, with pity?
He only thought of his life after the rings were exchanged
When the rings were removed
My child gave me a look ... O Lord.
Do you remember then, how you cried like a dog?
Just because it happened once, does it mean it's always the case, Rama?
Ah, we can only hope it doesn't happen
In any case, we can ask his relatives to come, right Mother?
This will be his second wedding. That's a sad thing about this match.
If it's a second wedding, it's a second wedding.
It'll at least be done.
We should ask her what she thinks
I asked. She likes him.
I'll be honest.
When he first told me about this, I did not agree
And it's not that I'm in agreement now.
If that's his fate, then so be it.
It's karma.
At his first weddding
at the auspicious moment
as we stepped out
a crow just fell and died in front of us, quivering.
It had collided with the electric cable.
Then itself, I told him that we shouldn't go ahead with the wedding
He didn't listen
And what happened?
She died of an electric shock, just like that!
Things like horoscopes, signs, and omens; they are not lies, it's the truth. Don't you think?
Well ... we should discuss our situation.
Huh? What else is there to talk about? We saw the girl, and that ritual is over.
An approximate date has been decided, right?
We don't need a ritual for that
We should consult an astrologer and settle the date.
Should we not have an idea about your expectations for gold and money?
Janardhan Nair is not such a cheapskate
It's not like I'm waiting for your gold and cash to live my life.
You give whatever you want to your child.
Just because we discuss some calculation for gold and cash, and we receive it from you, it doesn't make a mute, not a mute, will it?
Father, what are you saying?
Why are you afraid of stating facts?
Isn't that right, Ramanathan Nair?
That's right
Then, we have nothing of significance to discuss
We should consult an astrologer and fix a date tomorrow itself
Ah, Vijaya
Ask mother and grandmother to come here
If they go anywhere, they just take root.
I want to reach there before deepaaradhanam
Today, I am relieved
Radha's situation was such a burden for me and now it's over.
You can't survive without this, can you Ramanettan?
Lately, this has become a daily affair
Have you decided to destroy yourself through drink?
Oh, the tears have begun
Today's such a happy day
Come, and sit here
Ah, listen to me, Ramani
Sit there
If one has a bit of this, who told you that one would be destroyed?
Do you know how comfortable it is to sing after having a bit of this?
The voice really comes through
Haven't you told me several stories of people whose lives have been ruined by drink?
And now, you!
Please don't cry
Why are you needlessly worrying me?
Music, itself, is an intoxicant
One who has experienced that intoxicant, will not be drowned by this one
Moderation is key
In excess, even amritham is poison
Can you tell me, for sure, that it is not in excess?
Oh, of course, I can say that
Earlier, after the concert, you were so drunk, you couldn't even stand straight
And then, a lie
about an elephant who went wild
Ah, so
he comes and unloads everything here, doesn't he?
Then, once, a mistake was made
And so, everyone should know?
Can you look me in the face and say that it was a mistake which was only made once?
You ...
Didn't you go to Panikar?
I just returned
Brother, you haven't answered my question
Are you cross-examining me?
Brother, you must forgive me
I must say this now
in front of sister-in-law
I do not have to right to scold or advise.
I'm begging you
You must stop this at least in the memory of our deceased father
Gopi ...
Are you making me out to be a drunkard?
It has ended.
Today itself, it has ended.
So, are you content?
Can we trust you?
Now, on whom do I have to swear?
There is no need to swear on anyone.
Just hold firm
I'm holding firm
I will not touch it henceforth
Enough?
Ah, so, how did it go?
I asked him to look at the date
The 30th seems to be have an auspicious hour
After that, we'll have to wait for a month
Then, let it be the 30th!
Also, we told Janardhan Nair, that it would be the 30th, right?
That's right
Then we don't need to change it and make him uncomfortable
Where on earth is Raman?
I saw him talking to Govindan Menon and Kurup
Where is Kunjunni?
He went to look for him
No need.
Get lost!
Brother, what is this?
No problem. There is no problem.
That Menon and Kurup got him drunk. The bastards!
Don't talk nonsense. I'm fine.
Raman, should your uncle have to see this?
It just happened ...
There's absolutely no problem
Switch on the mic.
Raise it, raise the curtain!
Is it time for them to be back from the concert?
No, it's only turning 11
Then, who could it be at this time?
What happened? Was the concert canceled?
Where is Father and Gopi, Ramanetta?
What happened there?
Where is everyone, Ramanetta?
Rama, tell us
What happened to my son?
Nothing has happened to Mother's son
He's probably singing and bringing down the house
But ... why didn't you sing tonight?
I don't understand what's going on
I ...
I have been defeated!
Everyone has gotten together and defeated me
You drank, didn't you?
I was betrayed
Raman was not able to keep his vow
What is it, Rama?
What is it that I'm hearing, Ramani?
He's the son of Ayanoor Devanarayanan Namboodri
who drinks?
to the point that he cannot sing at a concert?
with the audience booing him?
O Lord ...
Has God kept me here to see and hear all this?
If Father were here
he would kill him
that's what would happen
Once I stood there watching
a person who had come to invite him to a concert get slapped across his face for coming drunk
There is no point in talking about old tales
If Father were here, he would have beaten him, or scolded him, or done whatever
Apart from tearfully pleading with him, what can we do?
Sister-in-law and I have begged him several times
How long has this been going on?
For a while
This medicine he keeps drinking is nothing else.
Oh Lord ...
Has he awoken, Ramani?
Yes.
And what did he say?
He cried a lot last night
And said that death is preferable.
Go to him
Ask your brother for forgiveness
I will ask him for forgiveness
But first tell me what was my mistake?
The people were heckling, and I only sang when I thought the performance would be ruined.
It wasn't to steal the limelight!
In any case, it was his concert
Didn't you sing without anybody's permission?
That, is a mistake.
It's not just in art and music, it's like that for anything.
So, I shouldn't have sung even thought the audience was heckling and the performance would've been ruined, right?
You should not have sung without your brother's permission
In your workplace
would you tolerate it, if your junior sat in your chair and worked?
In a government job
it might not be a big thing
but in arts
it's a very big thing
You must respect your Guru
Don't you think?
Brother ...
Stop ... there is no need for that.
I heard that the concert was phenomenal
It was not bad
If you neglect the fact that I was not able to touch your feet and start.
What is the meaning in all that?
Yesterday, after the concert
the music committee honored me with a gold shawl.
As this is my first token of honor
it belongs to you
Please accept it and bless me
Why do you need my blessings now?
You can keep it.
Here, in my closet, there's no room for these gold shawls.
You are punishing me, aren't you?
You are my guru, and my father
if I have unknowingly committed a mistake
I beg your forgiveness
Forgiveness?
You didn't do anything wrong, did you?
When everyone told me that
it didn't seem like it
but
now I believe so
When the people were heckling
and when I could not bear to watch your rhythm and voice quaver anymore
I couldn't help but sing
Good
Not missing the opportunity, was definitely a good thing.
Only they are victorious
That's not a mistake
In the past, during the Kurukshethra War
after putting down his bow and arrows
pointing at Karnan whose chariot was stuck in the mud
Krishna said
"There,
this is the chance."
Not foregoing that opportunity is Arjunan's victory
You won
I ...
What can I say?
From one point of view, you're right
From another point of view, it's not that right
Ah you're early today. Let's go?
I heard that Kallur Gopinathan did extremely well?
Oh, after a concert, you're so conceited?
Can't you smile a bit?
Please be quiet. Isn't there a limit to your jokes.
What?
Uncle, tell me what I should do.
I will never sing again. Is that enough?
What are you saying?
A singer, who chooses to not sing again?
Then, what is the point of that life?
Isn't it better to just die?
It is a preparation for that
if it is atonement for the sins that I have committed.
What an ill-fated pronouncement, Gopinatha
What happened for you to have such thoughts?
Tell us what happened, Gopietta
What happened, Father?
I know nothing, daughter
Something has been said between brothers
Can you please tell us?
Instead of just worrying us?
Brother says that when an opportunity presented itself
I deliberately defeated him.
What can I do to him?
Tell me in a way that I can understand
He's talking about yesterday's concert
Oh I see
If Brother is drunk, and cannot sing, what should Gopiettan have done?
Is it his fault for singing now?
That's exactly what I said
With all the drinking, he must have acquired the habits of drunkards
Unwanted thoughts, and actions
Don't you know how that coconut tree climber, Velayithan, behaves?
He beats up that poor Kathu in the evening after drinking
Every day, he has a different reason
For me, it's when I think of my daughter ...
Can you please go inside?
What an example
The coconut tree climber, Velayithan
Normal women at least have some sense. Well, her head is full of play sand anyway.
If it's play sand, then it's play sand.
Just look at what "people with sense" are doing and saying
Don't worry about any of this
When someone who is better than you comes
it can happen to anyone
In that case, I'm not so amazing
You will surpass your brother and your father
I am sure of it.
Shouldn't Brother take joy in that, Father?
He will be happy
Raman is only capable of that
I know it
Go to work in peace
I made a mistake
If you keep needling me about it, will the mistake be fixed?
All I'm saying is that this shouldn't happen again
I got it!
Who would commit an error knowingly?
It just happened ...
Everyone, please forgive me
I will fix this. Isn't that enough?
That's enough
Humans who do not make mistakes do not exist, do they?
Similarly, Gopinathan is also very worried
You should not hurt him
Isn't there anyone here who sees my pain?
Every second, I sting and burn
I can't meet people outside
I'll have to answer people's questions
Does he want this?
He didn't sing to implicate you!
We escaped the audience because of that
I agreed with that
I have no complaints about that
He saved me, right?
What luck
Because of that he has only profited
Let him grow
and surpass Father
Regardless, when he came to apologize ...
This is not something we need to discuss right now!
We don't have much time till Radha's wedding
That must be conducted beautifully
Exactly. Everyone should come together and make it a success
Heeranda ...
Call a carpenter to fix that spot
We need to clean this place after fixing these broken and worn out sections
Just tell me how much paint you need, and we'll buy it today or tomorrow
Start working as soon as possible.
Let's not have a panic attack at the last minute
OK, get going
Radha, ask them to give Uncle something to drink
Are your hands aching? I'll write some.
A loss of strength. It's because I haven't eaten.
You've got the journalists eating out of your hand, huh?
They're raving about you.
I heard
You just heard about it?
You didn't see it?
No.
Here.
You didn't let me know about your first concert?
At least your debut went well. That's enough.
It wasn't a debut.
It was a mistake.
A mistake?
Yes
Brother was supposed to sing at that concert
He drinks once in a while
I've mentioned it before
He went overboard this time
When he sang, and it didn't work out and the people started heckling, I stepped in
Brother was very depressed
He believes that I deliberately took advantage of the opportunity for my own gain
Your brother is really something
It's a complex, of sorts.
Everyone has a time
Nobody can sit on the throne forever; eventually, they have to step down
When his time ended
alcohol just emerged as a reason
You must not worry and throw away your future over this
My brother is dearer to me, than my future
He chanted the first notes of music to me
He made Gopinathan, the Kalloor Gopinathan these reporters talk about
I just want to learn under my brother's tutelage
Stop butchering it!
You really are inconveniencing me
Why, are you tired?
Do you always want to prepare cumin water and give it to everyone?
Just practice for a few days, and it will be fine
It's not about getting it right
Then?
It weighs on my mind
Our Gopinathan ...
What weighs on my mind doesn't bother you
Right?
I'll get somebody else?
I'll decide that!
You just do as you're told. Understood?
When Gopi is available, why are you needlessly bothering Kunjunni?
Now that he has started to sing by himself
it's not right to ask him to sing together or assist
Perhaps, he doesn't feel like it?
Rama, are you talking about Gopi?
Mother ...
Even if someone is your brother or son, you must respect, whom you must respect.
He's has a bigger name than me
He's assisted by someone through him music does not flow through
Move aside!
Gopi, get in there
No.
I'm training him
If I happen to get another concert
I need to still fill my stomach
You're getting rid of me, aren't you?
You don't need to see it like that
You'll get plenty of concerts in the future
It's not good for you to assist me
That's also true. You should see what's in the papers.
Oh I forgot!
Did you see what's printed?
What is it, brother?
Our Gopi's picture!
The press has great things to say about him!
Look here
Radha, look at this!
It wasn't there in the paper we get here
It wasn't in the paper at home either
It's only published in the Mathrbhumi
I borrowed it from another house
Look, son
Ah, I saw, I saw
I'll just show Father and Ramani and return.
Ah, OK.
Nowadays...
It's not that hard to become famous
but excessive praise
will only stunt growth
it's good to remember that.
Haven't you gone to bed yet?
Do you want some coffee?
No
Looks like Kunjunni is sleepy
Sister-in-law ...
Yes?
Kunjunni learned to assist quickly, didn't he?
Have I committed such a grave crime to earn such contempt?
Do you think you made a mistake?
Isn't that what everyone says?
Don't include me with everyone
Don't think that I didn't try to talk to him about you
I tried
He should try and understand, right?
Alcohol is capable of altering people's minds, isn't it?
In some way, this was a blessing
He's determined now
to regain his reputation
He doesn't drink at all now!
And he practices
Didn't he have a tremor in his voice before?
That has lessened now
Good
Let him despise me
It's fine
At the Thyagaraj festival
I just want to see Brother sing and triumph
Forgive me
I have seen you someplace
I cannot remember
I belong to the Mahalingam Coimbatore Thayagaraj Music Committee
Ah yes, I remember now. Please sit.
Please sit here.
I'm Sudhakharan. My home is in Palakkad.
I had received the notice before
This time the festival is truly a festival!
Ananthapoorthy, Balasubramaniam, and so many great singers are there!
Yes, that's right
There's a small problem in our usual program
The people from my generation don't have a problem
But there are a lot of young people in the committee. This young generation!
They have a request
They want your younger brother, Kalloor Gopinathan, in your place at the concert
Gopinathan instead of Ramanathan?
What nonsense are you spouting?
It was a sudden change
Please cooperate with us
I must cooperate, by not singing, right?
That's not true, sir.
We've heard good things about your brother.
People say that he's even better than your Father
He has only performed in one concert
That's enough, right?
I was there
The concert went well and we saw some things as well
For seven years
you have sung every time
The regulars will get tired of it
Besides
You do not have to return the advance
In our advance performance, we'll have a concert for you
Do you need to hurt me so?
No need
Rama, Rama ..
Hello, sir
Hello
What's the problem?
The problem is ...
The problem is nothing other than
for the Coimbatore concert
they just want you.
Me?
Yes.
And, what about Brother?
They don't want him.
Sir, that's our wish
Please cooperate.
No
I will not come
What can we say to console Raman now, O Lord?
You know how it is
We only want the event to succeed
We though Ramanathan sir would be happy if we invited his younger brother
If not, we will invite someone else
What do you say?
No
I will not sing
Not just at your event
Any event
Gopi ...
That's right, Uncle
I will, once and forever more, abandon music
I will end it by singing the Mangalam
And for that, you must play for me
Stop this. A singer who vows never to sing.
Isn't death better than that?
Never mind, Uncle
Brother is there
I will wash my face and legs
Appu is worried about you
Rama, Gopi will end it with the Mangalam
He will never sing again, apparently
I'm the one who should end it all with the Mangalam
Why does he need to do it?
Tell him not to sing it, Rama
Tomorrow, everyone will speak ill of you
Your father's soul will not forgive you, Rama
Rametta ...
Appu is our second son
You always said that our eldest son was Gopi
He has only sung what you taught him
He has only sat at your feet
Shouldn't we be happy to see him surpass even you and Father?
Yes
To end this sacrifice,
You do not need your brother's permission
Nor your Guru's permission.
Is that the case?
If you do not despise me
you must obey me.
You must sing
Surpassing me and Father
should be your goal
You may offer the dakshina
The dakshina</i.
is myself
There's a lot of kasava
There isn't any on this side
These are nice saris, right Mother?
This one is really good.
This is too much!
Let it be.
All of them have an old person's taste
None of us selected them
It was a young person
your Gopi
Ah, say that!
Then, how else can he improve?
I told him that I'd come with him
If only he listened. That Gopi!
Grandfather's taste is more tolerable than this
I think he has arrived
I'll teach him a lesson
What's the problem with this one?
I'm just messing with him, Mother
If Gopi gets angry, let him get angry
How was the concert?
I didn't dishonor Father's or Brother's name
It went well.
It didn't just go well, it was brilliant.
Didn't you see his garland and bouquet?
Where's Brother?
He headed out to Mannarkadu yesterday
saying that he had to meet someone
He hasn't returned
Brother had come to Coimbatore
Really? Didn't I tell you, Ramani, that he couldn't not go?
He attended the concert
He was really happy
He took of this necklace of Father's and put it on me
I looked for him everywhere after the concert
I thought he'd be here by now
He'll be here before evening
What? Mother and daughter have locked up the house and are here?
Well, how long can we wait for someone?
You said you'd be back before noon
Never mind that, I'll drop by home and head back
Now, why are you going there?
We've brought your mundu, shirt and everything else
When there's a hundred things to do here
Here, you go
I already have one, give it to Mother
Take it
Go ahead and take it
Really? All this bashfulness in your old age. Just take it
Take it!
Oh, be still
We've been pushing everything, day after day
we're really in a tight place now
Father, we still have 3-4 days
Just because we have a list, should we buy all these vegetables and let them wither?
We just need to buy them the day after tomorrow
Will gold wither?
Have you even bought that?
We'll buy it tomorrow, Grandfather. Let's just wait for Brother
Kutta, this asfoetida which you've set aside might be a bit too much
Grandfather asked me to keep it there.
Regardless of who told you to do it, it's still your responsibility
Gopi ...
Raman still isn't back
He'll be back; he left to get something done, didn't he?
Ramani is really worried
Sister-in-law, why are you so nervous?
Brother will be here soon
I'm afraid
that he's drunkenly fallen somewhere
Now, it's even worse than before
At the concert
He was ... quite drunk
He has no control
He has bought a closet full of bottles
He always wants to drink
And I offer no resistance
He asked, how does it matter now, if he drinks or doesn't drink
Gopi ...
Shouldn't someone go inquire after him?
Where do we even start looking for him?
He must have come home straight from Coimbatore
He must have gone to Mannarkadu from there
Still, the time for his return has passed
And there are so many things which need to be done here
All the relatives will start to arrive tomorrow
In any case, Kuttan, you should go to Mannarkadu
I'll go
We'll check out places he may frequent over here
He must be drinking with some people
Apart from that, where can he go?
Isn't that Krishnettan?
This is Gopinathan
We're calling from Thrissur
Did Ramanettan drop by?
OK, has he dropped by since?
Are there any places he might have gone to in Ernakulam?
No, there's no other news
He hasn't been home in 2 days
Can you look into this?
You're coming for the wedding, right?
Alright
He hasn't reached Ernakulam
If he did, he would have dropped by to visit Krishnettan
Oonietta?
Oonietta, this is Gopinathan
It's about Brother
No, please listen to me
OK, I wanted to discuss something else
Oonietta!
He won't let me get a word in!
He's got a bone to pick with us
because we didn't invite him personally
But you didn't ask him if he was there
That was obvious from what his way of talking
How much?
Kunjunni
Give him this money
Shouldn't we let the police know?
What's the need for that?
Apart from scaring Ramani and Devu
When we get home, he'll already have arrived
Why don't we look around in Coimbatore?
Ah, that's right
Let's go straight to Coimbatore
We already searched in Coimbatore
If we go, who will get things ready for the wedding?
Don't we have to pick out the gold tomorrow?
It's OK if we do that after 2 days
We just need it in time for the wedding
Gopi, if you're not at home now, everyone will worry
I'll go to Coimbatore
That is best.
You guys should go home.
If you insist, Kunjunni should go
Let's go via Guruvayur
and ask that Menon if he saw him
OK, let's go
Has Brother arrived?
No ...
He hasn't reached Mannarkadu's Gopalettan's place
Apparently, he received a letter saying that he would visit
Now, where else can we search for him?
I searched the entire area
and the areas around it
He hadn't been to any of those places
Now where else can we look for him?
Maybe we should check at Nambeeshan from Kotak?
He occasionally hangs out there
Would he do that without letting anyone know, especially during all the wedding preparations?
In any case, you should go investigate
You have the vehicle, right?
I'll go
Did you see sister-in-law?
I did
I told her about where you went
How could I not tell her?
Why is he making us eat coals like this?
Gopi ...
In any case, Kuttan, you should get going
Uncle ...
You should go with him
Did you receive any news?
He must be in Coimbatore
He has a lot of friends there
Kunjunni, has gone there
O Lord ...
Where do we look for him?
Who can we ask?
Don't cry, daughter
God won't let any harm come to him
Sister-in-law ...
Please don't needlessly cry and worry Appu as well
Brother will come
It's only been 2 days since he left
There must have been a pressing situation
Otherwise, would he be so late?
When my insides trembled, I suspected as much
something misfortune was coming
If something happened in a foreign land
who would know?
Grandfather, can you please keep quiet?
What misfortune has happened here?
Please don't cry
They're just
trying to figure it out
Where would he go?
Everything will go beautifully
Tomorrow, when Brother arrives
we can go
get the gold
then the sandals
box
pick up all the clothes we gave for sewing
Right?
Please don't cry
Go to sleep
Go
There's no place in Coimbatore that I haven't searched
There are many who saw him at the concert
He's not in Coimbatore, Kota or Thrissur
Now, where can we look for him?
Could something have happened to my son, Gopi?
Uncle, don't say anything like that
What's this, Gopi?
Like small kids
We must face whatever happens
We should notify the police
Let them investigate
If we notify the police
they might want to ask Priya or mother something
Isn't it better to let them know beforehand?
I can't bear to deal with any of this
Gopi ...
Why don't you talk to sister-in-law?
At least drink some water, Ramani
Why don't you tell her?
How can she stay alive if she doesn't eat something?
I'll tell her, Ammai, you should go
Sister-in-law ...
We have looked everywhere we can look
We have learned nothing
Shall we notify the police?
We can advertise in the newspaper
My son is now fatherless
Can you please come with me?
Please come
I want to talk to you about something
Gopietta, if you also start
who will comfort Ammai, Radha, and sister-in-law?
We don't know what happened
Everyone is needlessly killing him with their words
Please listen carefully
This is not the time to cry
We must find out the truth
What, what is it, tell me.
I saw an article in the newspaper
3 days ago, at night
in Palakkad, somebody
was run over by a vehicle
The body has been held at a mortuary for 2 days
The name and address is not known
When I read about the person's particulars
I had a suspicion
When I had that suspicion
I tore it out and kept it aside
Hit-and-run in Palakkad
The possibly 45-year old victim
passed away in an accident on the road
The vehicle which hit him drove away without stopping
With a dark complexion
and of height, 5'5"
in a white mundu and jubba
The body has been held (after the postmortem)
in the mortuary
Ah, it's today's paper and someone has torn out something
I haven't seen Ramanathan sir yet
I'm here on time
We must get the ginger, and onion for the meal now
The kids will be here by the evening
If you can procure the goods, we can start work
Why are you quiet?
Nothing, we can think about it
Think about it? Why?
Is something wrong?
Oh, not at all
Ah, Gopi
Please tell your brother that I have arrived
I'll tell him, right after he arrives
I must go to a place
Once I'm back, we can buy everything
Uncle ...
Please open a room for them
Where are you off to?
I'll tell you when I'm back
Is Devi going with you?
Yes.
Please don't go anywhere
I won't
I'll call the Palakkad SP and give him the news
What journalists write doesn't have to be true
Don't worry about it
If it's the truth ...
How can I bear it?
Devi seems to have more courage than you
No matter what, we must bear it
Are you really this soft?
Let's do this
I'll come as well
If he goes, it'll really be a problem
I'm the Calicut RDO
Harikumar
Isn't the CA here?
the CA has gone home.
Should I call him?
No need.
Please sit
OK
Sit
About why I'm here
Didn't somebody die a 2-3 days ago from a road accident?
I heard that his body is held at the mortuary
We suspect that it may belong to a relative
Oh, sir
We moved it from the mortuary this morning
Since nobody came to claim it
the DM from the hospital insisted that we remove it immediately
Do you have any photographs?
Yes, we do
We have secured the photographs and material objects
Please bring them.
Yes, sir
Gopi ...
In some horrible circumstance, if they do belong to him
you must not make a scene
Gopi ...
It was an accident, wasn't it?
Yes, sir
At night
he passed away at midnight
A lorry hit him
The car which was behind
reported it here
Since the license plate wasn't illuminated
they were unable to note the number
They drove off without stopping
The wheel ran over his head
It was smashed in
Shouldn't you arrange to inform everyone at home?
I must let them know
Sir
I would like to
take my brother's body home
Like a nameless corpse ...
If we have to retrieve the body again
We'll need a special order from the Collector
We must get it
I need to conduct the final rites
We will take care of it
But I doubt that we can take it back today
It's quite late in the day
We will certainly take it back tomorrow
We will now head home
That is best. Go home.
Once you're there, just send someone over here to take care of it.
OK?
I'll take care of things here
Do not delay
Go ahead
Devi ...
How do I tell them?
How can we not tell them?
Even though he's my brother-in-law
I only call him "high priest"
Towards the end, he had an inclination towards ascetism
And he'd ask me
Hey, Parammu
Why don't you leave your family and children,
embrace music and become an ascetic?
I can't bear to be away from my kids
It didn't happen to father or son, I'm happy
Uncle ...
Where on earth were you?
Did you forget that a wedding is going to be conducted here?
Someone has been sent to look for you
Couldn't you have told us where you were going?
Oh Gopi, there isn't a place we haven't looked for you
What a great time you guys have chosen to roam around
Sister-in-law ...
Brother ...
Your brother really gave us a scare
Nothing has happened to him
A letter has arrived
It's addressed to you
When I saw the handwriting, I opened it.
Do you mind?
Even if you do, I don't care
He has assumed some things
God isn't so blind
Stop dreaming and come!
Here, read this and take a look
I need to go to the kitchen
I don't understand anything
Please read it
Dear brother,
The concert
was magnificent
You will surpass Father
To you,
an unnecessary jealousy
was upon me
To anyone who complains
how they feel towards victors
an emotion
In any case
Today, I am completely content
I have only one desire left
Together,
we should hold another concert
Today, I do not have the ability for that
Alcohol
has left me in a terrible state
I need deliverance from it
By entrusting body and mind to God,
I'm going on a journey
From Kanyakumari, to the river Ganga
Forgetting everything
A journey with only music as my focus
It's an ascetic's journey
I thought of starting this journey after Radha's wedding
But with every passing moment
My mind's resolve weakens
After all, you're there ... for everything.
Please explain the situation to Radha
Her wedding was
my biggest dream
To sister-in-law,
you must tell everything
She will understand me
After all,
she's meant for me.
To Grandfather,
Mother,
Ammama and Appu,
ask them to pray for me
Your brother
will return as your old Ramettan
That is certain.
Gopietta ...
Cease this
Everyone is so happy now
We cannot destroy that
If not, then what?
We can also accept this
Brother has gone on a pilgrimage
He will return
Gopi!
Did you hear the news?
In any case, he's alive!
That's enough for me
At least, it was for a good thing
God made him do it
After his pilgrimage
after discarding his unwanted habits
he will return without delay
In the past
his father also had this idea
To become an ascetic
It's because I didn't allow it
If he had told me, I wouldn't have allowed it either
After having considered him lost
the joy of knowing that you haven't lost anything
that is truly happiness, you know
Why do you look so off?
Probably because his brother left the responsibilities of the house to him. Let him learn
He was just loafing about till now
He had planned to have a blast without any accountability forever
Now
He must conduct the wedding as the head of the family
Sister-in-law's, Appu's
Grandfather's
and Ammai's affairs need to be taken care of
And then this poor soul's
You guys are joking around here?
Things need to move quickly now
Have you given those men any water?
I had given them some water before
Not that, Mother, alcohol ...
Do you call that water as well?
Be it water, or buttermilk, it is normal to give it to them
Brother's closet has 3-4 bottles in it
Here, give it to them
Gopietta, Appu.
Uncle, why did Father abandon me?
Let your Father be
I'm here for you
Whatever you want
Just tell me
I've explained it but he doesn't understand, Gopi
Appu, Father will return quickly to see us
Isn't that right, Gopi?
That's right.
Come.
I'll get you some food
Ah, Gopi
Brother has kept some cash there
At least, we should get the gold by tomorrow
Isn't the wedding on the day after tomorrow?
It won't do for you to just stand there
Come
In between heaven and hell,
I seemed to have found myself, O Lord
What all acts I need to put on
Then let's call everyone, and tell them
That Brother was run over, and crushed by a vehicle to his death
Gopietta ...
Radha's wedding must go on
If it does not happen at the auspicious time
You know his father's behavior
Do you think there's a chance for this to work out again?
If this does not happen
How will Radha bear this?
How do I bear this?
You must
For your brother
Wasn't it his biggest dream?
Radha's wedding?
It must happen
Thinking of our predicament
Brother's soul must be crying
Look
Isn't this great?
Isn't this nice, Mother?
Gopietta ...
Shouldn't we tell Harikumar sir the news?
We must
Now, when can we do that?
In the evening
he will be here with the body
How do I let him know?
What reason can I give to leave?
I'll think of something and tell them
You must leave now
Otherwise it will become a huge problem
Give this money to Ammama
I'll get it home
Sir
We have it. It's packed with medicine since it has decomposed a bit.
The situation is in a weird state, sir
What happened?
Everyone is thrilled at home
A letter from brother arrived
A letter he wrote before his death
In the letter, he says that he's going for a pilgrimage
Everyone at home is thrilled after reading that
My sister's wedding is tomorrow
It was my brother's biggest dream
I could not bring myself to tell them
Good
It's best if it stays that way
Let the planned wedding happen
The dead have escaped their burdens
It is well that you thought about the living
Now, brother's body
cannot be taken home
That is a problem
It has already been packed
How can we refuse them now?
It's not that we don't want it. We do.
All his final rites must be conducted
Everything must be done correctly
And nobody must know
Why don't we cremate him near the Bharatha stream?
That's exactly what I had in mind
He really loved the Bharatha stream
Stir it well
Everything is OK, right?
How did it go?
We cremated it
Where?
At the Bharatha stream
Gopietta ...
Do not falter
I told everyone that you went to Guruvayur
Gopi!
Where were you?
I was on an important ...
So, what's going on?
Cheriyamma, Anu, Mini and Devan have all come
Ah, we're happy
Hey, isn't there any of that?
Ah, no
It's a wedding, there should be some of that!
If Ramanathan were here, it wouldn't have been a problem at all
Is it true that he's an ascetic now?
Or is it because there was a falling out between the two of you?
Uncle, please leave us alone
You and your jealousy
Won't you leave us in peace?
Come, Gopietta
Hmmm, you're truly your mother's daughter
Come, come
You're really something else; couldn't you have told us before leaving?
Where did you duck out to?
I went to Guruvayur
Don't you know that your brother isn't here?
Shouldn't you be here?
Everyone who arrives asks me
What would Radha think?
Should she feel the lack of her elder brother's presence?
What's up with you?
You have the funny face of a monkey who ate some ginger
Oh, you're just imagining things
Be that as it may, if you call him a monkey, you'll have to deal with me!
Sure, sure
What is this Gopi?
This is a house of great singers
Forget a concert, there isn't even any singing
Come, we should celebrate
I'm not feeling well
If his brother were here, you'd see
there'd have been music and celebration
this is like a house mourning someone's death
Come
We'll get you feeling better
Otherwise, Radha will feel bad
Ramani!
I'm coming!
Devi ...
The fires that we lit have not even died
How can I sing before that happens?
I can't take it anymore
My chest and neck are so tight it hurts
Gopi!
They're looking for you over there
Why is this girl hanging around him?
In case someone kidnaps him!
You must keep it together
If you slip
You will not be able to hold on
I cannot
I'm faltering
Pray to your brother for strength
Gopi!
Is that all?
There's nothing left?
No.
Ah, then get going
And like that, it ended brilliantly
Don't we have to go soon?
It's been a week since we locked up the house
Sure, we'll go tomorrow. After all, Raman isn't here.
I share Devi's opinion
You concealed it till now
Leave it as it is
For how long must I bear this burden?
You must try to understand my situation where I cannot even break down and cry
It's not that I do not understand
Your sister-in-law
Isn't this a shock she cannot handle?
And we won't have answers to any of their questions
Many will blame you
Perhaps, cruel accusations will be made
What accusations?
People won't even hesitate to say that you murdered him
Murder?
I only said that it's possible
Many will be suspicious because you concealed his death
That's the time we live in
Anyone who knows Gopiettan
wouldn't say that, sir.
It's not that they will, they might
I was just thinking outside the box
Even if they make such a mistake
the police have records
People will say that they were fabricated
Furthermore, my involvement, will strengthen that accusation
Right now, everyone at home is relieved
Let it be that way; that is best.
That's how it should be, Gopietta
Brother is gone
Now
what's the point in knowing?
what's the point in not knowing?
In any case, the rituals have to be conducted
Appu must
conduct the ritual
Otherwise, Brother's soul will not attain salvation
Isn't all that just a belief?
It may be that
But I must get it done
Like an orphaned ghost
my brother's body
alone
was put to rest without anyone knowing
His soul must not also be orphaned
It must not founder searching for rice and lemons
What will you tell Appu if he asks?
I'll have to tell him some lie
Till now, wasn't I telling and enacting lies?
I will get this done through some lies as well
What happened, Appu?
Uncle, you lied to me
Whose final rituals did you make me do?
Grandfather's
Why did he say that it was for my father?
He also said my father's name
Ramanathan
My father is dead, isn't he?
No
Lies!
How did he die?
Who killed him?
Who?
Appu!
He was not murdered
Just listen to me
Don't say anything
I don't want to hear anything. It's all lies
Appu!
All you say are lies.
Appu, get back here!
Appu!
Is Appu telling the truth, Devi?
Mother ...
It's true that Brother died
but it was only an accident!
Then, why did you conceal it?
I told you
I cannot believe anything you say
O Lord ...
Devi ...
Appu?
You have made him fatherless, haven't you?
Mother, don't speak like that
Gopietta ...
Nobody understands us
Sister-in-law?
I told her everything that happened
But ...
How will my daughter ever know peace?
If she curses you in this pained state of mind
You will not remain living
I am prepared to receive any curse
Gopietta, please don't meet anyone now
I must
I cannot hide and run anymore
I cannot act anymore
How could you betray us like this, son
Grandfather!
I ...
No
I don't want to hear it
I don't want to hear anything
Didn't you step over his body to conduct this wedding?
If you had said one word, would I have stood by this?
When my Raman is lying dead
O Lord ...
What all did you make us do?
You didn't even show my son's body to me!
Didn't you bury him like an orphan, like someone with nobody?
How can I bear this?
Tell me, how can I bear this?
Mother
No!
I don't want to hear anything!
Mother ...
Get out of my sight!
Sister-in-law ...
Now, for your condemnation
I have the strength to bear it
You can curse me
I will take on any sin
Are you not satisfied?
Now, what disguise do you want me to put on?
How do you want me to act?
Even when I was in the throes of pain
I didn't cry
I laughed
I sang holding back endless grief
I did everything he wanted
Radha was married
Sister-in-law ...
Whatever I did was wrong
it was cruel
What penance should I perform?
What fire should I be consumed by?
I know you better
than anyone else
At least now
as you have wanted to, can you not burst into tears?